In this lesson we are diving into object typing and nested structures in TypeScript, which
is a core skill for modeling real world data, to whether you are building a user profile
or perhaps a product catalog or a configuration file, TypeScript is going to help us define
clear, safe and scalable object shapes, so we are going to start off with a simple object
type.
Now we have already had a look at type AVs and interfaces, and you can model an object
on either the type AVs or the interface, and I have just chosen to use the type and the
AVs here for user, and we have three properties, id, name and is admin.
So this defines the shape of a user object, and TypeScript is going to enforce that every
object matches this structure.
Now to use the actual object, we can create an object like, let's say Alice and Alice
is of type user, and then we can define the properties for Alice, so we can set id, and
the id could be maybe u123, and then the name of Alice, and finally is admin, and set
to true.
If we get to use a property, or we use the wrong type, TypeScript is going to help us
out.
Now, let's talk about optional and read only properties, and now we want to define
perhaps an optional property.
Let's say, for example, we want to have a description property, and we just give it
a question mark, and then the actual type.
So this now is optional, and you can see that TypeScript is not complaining that we haven't
described, and we haven't supplied the description property, but of course, if we want
to, we can add a description property here and say Alice in Wonderland or something.
Let's now define another prior type, and let's have a type of product, and this type is
going to have a string, just like before, you can have a name, and this time we're going
to have a price, which is going to be a number, and also again might want to have a description
property that's optional, so we have description.
If a question mark, and it's a stop type string, now if we also want to have a read only
property that we could obviously read from, then we need to change this syntax very slightly,
and once we say read only, first of all, then give it the name of the property, so in this
case, we're going to have a read only property called school, and the type is of type string.
This cannot be changed, that'd be read.
So the two things to bear in mind is the question mark for optional, and this read only
syntax here, the specified a read only property.
We also might want to have like a nested structure, because at the moment we have a very
simple structure, just one level deep.
Let's try a model, a customer, which has an address.
So first of all, we're going to start off with just the address type, so the address type
is going to have a street, or type string, city, and also a zip code, or type string.
Now we're going to model our customer, so the customer is going to have a name, going to
have an email address, while they're also going to have an address.
Now for that, we can simply just give the name of the property, address, and then the actual
type that we've already predefined, in this case, address.
And of course, we could define a customer, because a const, Alice is a customer, and Alice
is of type, customer, and now we can define our name, the name is Alice, she has an
email address to Alice at something, and then we can define the actual address.
So how do we actually specify the properties, the values for these address properties?
We do that as a JSON object, so we specify the address, then the codey braces, and then
we can give it the things like street, let's say street to one, two, three, and then
be city, is city, et cetera, et cetera, et cetera.
Of course, we can give it to keep its TypeScript happy, let's just give it a zip code
of one, two, three.
Let's now walk through another example, and this time we are going to create ourselves
a profile object or profile type, so we have a type of profile, and in our profile type,
we're going to have a username or type string, we're going to have some settings, and
for this we can now specify a kind of deeply nested object, and under this we're going
to have, use the curly braces, and we're going to have a theme property, the theme property
can be light or the pipe symbol going to be dark, and also going to have a property of
notifications, which is sets to type a boolean.
Now we can also define our type as a nested types as well, so rather than as a separate
type, like we did for address, we can kind of do it in line, so we could have a type
as a property of username, which is set to a type of string, and we can have a settings,
and we now create a curly brace, and inside our settings we're going to have a theme property,
the theme property is going to have a string of light or dark, and we're also going to
have a notification property, which is of type boolean, and now we can simply define a
natural instance of the object, so const user, set to profile, and now we can specify the
properties itself, so username, say Tim, settings, getting curly braces, we can specify this,
so the theme is now light, and the notifications we are going to set to true, and now let's
work on an even more complex example, which is a type of order, and this is going to have
a customer object, or customer, a type inside it, as well as an array of items, so we set
up a type of order, so inside our order type, we're going to have an order ID, or type
string, then inside of that, then we're also going to have a type of customer, and the type
of customer, is going to be an object in itself, which we're going to have a name property,
and inside of that, we're going to have another type of contact, which is new address,
and also a optional phone number, so again, put it a question mark to make it optional,
type string, and we also want to have the items, or this particular order, which we can
do by defining an array, and again, right back at the start, we learnt to an array by doing
some curly, there's some square brackets here, so that is now an item array, which we
can need, the product ID, or type string, and also a quantity, or type a number, and now
you can see how we can do this, or nesting of the types, allows us to very nicely describe
more complex objects through the TypeScript, now instead of defining the actual embedded
types like this, just to make it clearer, and for the developers looking at your objects
is better to be able to explicitly define the types into smaller chunks that we can then
use in a more complex object, so we want to define first of all a type of contact, which
has got our email, and also our optional phone, which has our email property, and also
our optional phone number, and we can now change where we have this contact here, that
becomes simply our type of contact, we now can work on the customer itself, so we can define
a customer type, customer type has a name of string, and the contact information, name
of string, and the contact of the type contact, so our customer can now be replaced,
remove the customer, and this becomes a type of customer, and now we can define another
type for all the items itself, now all the items has a product ID of string, the quantity
of string, and the quantity of number, and now items array becomes an array of order item,
and now looking at this object is a lot clearer to understand what's going on, rather than
what we heard before, so again, it's better to break up our types into smaller types,
and then build that up to make create more complex objects, so object typing is basically
how we model real world data and TypeScript as an example here, we've learned how to define
object shapes, and we've also learned about optional and read new properties, as well as
nested structures which give clarity and safety, in the next lesson we're going to learn
all about reusing components with type safety using a feature known as generics and TypeScript.